<page>
<paragraph number="1"> Digital Banking
On 12 February, the Arab Bank and the Palestinian Telecommunications Group (PALTEL) jointly launched the first “neobank” in Palestine, Reflect.1 It was first launched in Jordan as a virtual bank that operates exclusively through digital channels, providing a range of services such as current accounts, fund transfers and payment of bills and utilities.
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="2"> Alignment with local needs and global trends
Compared to traditional digital banking, neobanks offer more convenient and accessible solutions, with a customer-centric approach and reduced operational costs.2 These factors allow more competitive pricing and rates for customers by avoiding the operational costs associated with physical branches. Furthermore, neobanks are able to supply digital services to non-digital banks. From this perspective, Reflect’s launch aligns with the Palestine Monetary Authority (PMA) strategy to facilitate the development of electronic payment methods and financial inclusion in Palestine.3
This new development is also in line with the global trend of convergence between telecommunications operators and retail banks.4 The partnership allows Arab Bank to expand its customer base by providing new and innovative digital banking solutions that correspond to the needs of different societal segments. It also creates an opportunity for PALTEL to expand its services in the digital banking space and offer more integrated solutions to its customers, in addition to those currently available through JawwalPay (Jawwal’s digital wallet).5 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="3"> Expected impact on fintech adoption
The use of technology among individuals and businesses in Palestine remains generally high, allowing the opportunity to expand the adoption of financial technology. Around 91.9% of economic establishments used a mobile phone in 2021 (92.6% in the West Bank and 90.5% in the Gaza Strip), and around 61.1% have access to the internet (69.9% in the West Bank and 47.7% in the Gaza Strip). Approximately 88% of individuals aged 10 years or older have access to the internet (91% in the West Bank and 44% in the Gaza Strip), and 71% own a smartphone (82% in the West Bank and 56% in the Gaza Strip).6 For both individuals and businesses, the potential for expanding fintech in Palestine appears promising.
The use of financial technology among individuals is already gaining traction, despite adoption rate starting from a low baseline. In 2022, only 3.3% of Palestinian adults (aged 18 and above) owned or used a digital wallet (2.9% in the West Bank and 4% in Gaza Strip).7 The PMA reported that the number of digital wallets owned by individuals reached 363,347 in Q3 2022, compared to 172,005 digital wallets in Q3 2021. The total value of these digital wallets also increased from $1.2m to $1.7m over the same period.8 Around 1.5m digital wallet transactions with a total value of $129.4m were carried out in the first nine months of 2022, compared to 397,000 transactions totalling $29.7m in the corresponding period in 2021.9
According to the latest financial inclusion data (from 2022), 15.1% of Palestinians aged 18 or above own or use at least one type of digital financial services, with 7.4% of Palestinian adults using online banking services, 11.3% using mobile banking services and 6.7% paying bills online.10 To put this data into perspective, the total percentage of Palestinian adults who hold or use a bank account stands at 34.8% (43.9% in the West Bank and 20% in the Gaza Strip). 
</paragraph>
</page>