<page>
<paragraph number="1"> In addition, offering user-friendly digital banking with reduced costs and improved services is expected to encourage more businesses to adopt digital payments. Currently, Palestine has a low rate of adoption of digital financial solutions, despite regulators’ and international organisations’ efforts to boost the uptake.11 A recent survey by the Palestine Central Bureau of Statistics (PCBS) showed that in 2021, around 14.4% of economic establishments in Palestine used digital payment methods, 17.1% in the West Bank and 9% in the Gaza Strip.12 When the remaining 85.6% of the surveyed economic establishments were asked about the reasons they opted not to use electronic payment methods, 75.2% stated that they are unwilling to use them, 19.6% said that they did not know that such services existed in Palestine, 17.4% complained about the high cost and 17.3% did not know how to use them. 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="2"> The provision of new digital banking services is also expected to help increase the expansion of e-commerce, which is currently being utilised by only 1.5% of businesses in Palestine (1.9% in the West Bank and 0.2% in the Gaza Strip). Generally, businesses in both areas rely almost entirely on cash on delivery, or COD (93.8% in the West Bank and 100% in the Gaza Strip). 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="3"> Banking sector performance remains sound
In the first half of 2022, banking sector capital (16.7% of risk- weighted assets) remained adequate, and profitability (10.4% return on equity) had recovered to above its pre-pandemic level, while non-performing loans (NPLs) remained steady at 4.2% of total loans.13 Preliminary estimates also indicate that the sector maintained its improved profitability in the second half of 2022.14 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="4"> In 2021, total revenues of the Palestinian banking sector reached $870.6m, an increase of 109.2% from 2011.15 Net interest income increased by 127.3% between 2011 and 2021 and is the main source of revenue for Palestinian banks, representing 72.6% of total bank revenue. Credit facilities, the main source of interest income, increased by 202.7% between 2011 and 2021.16 Net banking fees, the second largest source of banking revenues (13.9% of banks total revenues in 2021), saw an 86.5% increase over the same period. 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="5"> The Palestinian banking system relies extensively on interest income and service fees to generate revenues. This is in contrast to international banks, which generally also rely on other sources of revenue, such as trading securities, investment banking and fiduciary activities, instruments which are limited in Palestine.17 The PMA’s recently-introduced ceilings on bank fees and commissions should encourage banks to seek new profit-generating opportunities.18 In the longer term, consolidated banking system net profits reached $197.8m in 2021, a 49.4% increase compared to 2011. Despite this growth in banks’ profits, profitability metrics such as the return on equity dropped from 11.2% in 2011 to 9.4% in 2021. Returns on assets registered a similar trend, reaching 0.9% in 2021, compared to 1.4% in 2011. 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="6"> Rising Labour Market Tensions
Since the start of 2023, there has been an increase in labour union protests demanding improved wages and labour conditions. Public sector teachers, doctors and engineers are demanding salary increases promised in previous wage negotiations.19
To make matters more complex, public sector employees, including teachers, engineers, and doctors, have been receiving only partial wages since November 2021. The Minister of Finance, Shukri Bishara, announced last year the PNA’s inability to pay wages in full due to the ongoing fiscal crisis.20 As a result, Bishara requested to postpone implementing any wage increase agreements with public sector employee unions, citing an ILS 840m increase in the PNA wage bill per annum. However, unions are now demanding the PNA fulfil its commitment to previously signed agreements.21 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="7"> Disruptions to vital social services
Crucially, the current wave of strikes involves employees in vital areas such as health and education. In both these sectors, employees have been persisting with demands, with no clear resolution in sight.
Public school teachers are now approaching the fourth week of strike action with overwhelming participation of almost 90% of public teachers.22 Teachers demanded the enforcement of last year’s strike demands, which included the democratisation of teacher representation and a 15% wage increase by January 2023, as well as an additional 5% increase by 2024.23 Other demands included linking overall salaries to real cost of living and guarantees that salaries are paid without prejudice.24 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="8"> On 1 February, the doctor’s union set a 50% price increase on medical examinations and called on private clinics and doctors to halt their dealings with health insurance companies until the latter have committed to covering the new rates.25 This decision led to a dispute between the union and Palestinian insurance companies relating to a 2018 agreement between the two parties that set limits for rate increases.26 On 19 February, a meeting was initiated by the Palestinian Ministry of Health to discuss the stand-off,27 resulting in the increase in the price of medical examinations being set at 20%.28 While this compromise could potentially alleviate the current deadlock, ordinary Palestinians will bear the consequences by paying higher premiums for private health insurance, while public resources needed to cover Ministry of Health referrals to private clinics due to limited capacity will be additionally burdened by the increase.29 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="9"> Persistent structural challenges
While around 95,000 people entered the Palestinian labour market in 2022, the market was only able to generate anadditional 51,000 jobs between 2021 and 2022. The Israeli labour market, however, absorbed an additional 47,000 workers, employing a total of 193,000 Palestinians by the end of 2022. The services sector is the largest employer in the local labour market, while the construction sector is the largest employer of Palestinians in Israel and Israeli settlements. 
</paragraph>

</page>