
<page>
<paragraph number="1"> According to Palestine Central Bureau of Statistics (PCBS), the unemployment rate stood at 24.4% in 2022, a drop from 26.4% in 2021. Unemployment remains persistently high among people aged 19-29 (48.3%), women (40%), and Gaza Strip residents (45%).30 The average unemployment period for West Bank residents is 12.3 months, compared to 21 months in the Gaza Strip.31 There is also a large gap in the labour force participation rate between the West Bank (47.5%) and the Gaza Strip (41%), and between men (70.7%) and women (18.6%). Total labour underutilisation - the unmet need for employment as a result of mismatches between labour supply and demand - reached 31% (or 500 000 people) in 2022.
In terms of labour protection, 65% of wage employees in the private sector are hired without a verbal or written contract, and 56% of female wage employees do not have paid maternity leave benefits. A striking 40% of wage employees in the private sector receive less than the new minimum wage (ILS 1,880) that came into force at the start of 2022 (19% in the West Bank and 89% in the Gaza Strip).32 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="2"> The National Employment Strategy 2021-2025
An international meeting on employment in Palestine between Palestinian government, the International Labour Organization (ILO) and the Arab League took place in Amman on 24 and 25 February sponsored by the German government,33 the meeting served as a platform for communication and coordination to support the implementation of the latest Palestinian National Employment Strategy (PNES), spanning 2021-2025.34 On the sidelines of the meeting Palestinian Minister of Labour Nasri Abu Jaish signed eight agreements with local and international bodies to support the implementation of PNES over the next three years, together worth $55m.35 The agreements aim to support vocational training and education and create job opportunities for youth and women across several sectors.36 A budget of $25m was allocated to the employment generation programmes, which aim to create 2,500 permanent and 3,000 temporary job opportunities over the next two years. This includes cash for work, temporary employment and support for SMEs and the self-employed.37 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="3"> The National Employment Strategy 2021-2025 aims to achieve ‘full employment’, reducing informal work, improving gender equality in the labour market, enhancing social protection for workers and increasing the participation of underrepresented groups in the labour force.38 It also paved the way for raising the national minimum wage from ILS 1,450 to ILS 1,880 per month (from approximately $437 to $567), which came into effect in 2022. However, progress has been slow and limited due to various challenges, including a lack of resources and funding, limited access to international markets, and ongoing political instability. 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="4"> Siniora’s New Factory in Saudi Arabia
On 23 February, at the 2023 Gulfood event in Dubai, Siniora Food Industries Company (Siniora) signed an agreement with the Saudi Authority for Industrial Estates and Technology Zones (MODON) to establish a chilled and frozen meat factory on a 25,000-square-metre land plot in Jeddah’s second industrial area. 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="5"> The new facility is expected to cost around $3 million and aims to meet the growing demand for such products in the Saudi market while helping Siniora expand its reach in regional markets.39 By manufacturing from within the Saudi market, Siniora aims to reduce its transportation costs, decrease delivery times and improve its responsiveness to the local market’s demand.40 The new facility will also allow Siniora to diversify its product range and introduce new products that cater to the local Saudi market’s preferences. It will also help Siniora avoid import duties and taxes, which can reduce its production costs and improve its competitiveness in the Saudi market.41 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="6"> Siniora’s expansion trajectory
The expansion of Siniora, a subsidiary of the Arab Palestinian Investment Company (APIC), into Saudi Arabia is part of the company’s long-term strategic plan to expand its operations in the Middle East and beyond.42 Siniora Food Industries has a long-standing history that began in 1920, when the company was founded in Jerusalem. Its commitment to producing high-quality deli meat products soon cemented it as a household name in the Middle East.43
In 1992, the company established a factory in Jordan to meet theincreasingdemandforitsproducts.Withtime,Siniora’s success led to it being acquired by the Arab Palestinian Investment Company (APIC), which allowed it to expand beyond Jordan and Palestine to supply markets across the region, including Syria, Lebanon, Saudi Arabia, the United Arab Emirates, Kuwait, Qatar, Oman, Yemen, and Bahrain.44 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="7"> In 2009, the company established the Siniora Trading Company to distribute its products in the Saudi market. In 2014, Siniora Gulf General Trading was established to enter the UAE market. Subsequently, in 2016, Siniora acquired the Dubai-based Diamond Meat Processing Company, further increasing its reach in the Middle East regional (GCC) market.45
Apart from expanding in the GCC market, Siniora has also expanded its business in Jordan and Turkey. In 2013, APIC established the Jordanian Poultry Company (JPC), which has since become one of the leading producers of poultry in Jordan. JPC’s success prompted APIC to expand its poultry business to Turkey, where it established a new facility in 2017. This expansion allowed APIC to expand its customer base beyond Palestine and Jordan. With its latest acquisition of a Turkish company, Tarakya, and signing this new agreement, Siniora is well placed to tackle new markets and solidify its position as a leading player in the meat and dairy industry.46 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="8"> February Trading
In February 2023, the Al-Quds index reached 657.6 points on the last day of trading, an increase of 2% from the previous month.47 During the month, a total of 9m shares with a total value of $16.8m were traded, marking a 59.4% and 58.3% drop in the number and value of traded shares, respectively, compared to January 2022. 
</paragraph>
</page>