<page> 
<paragraph number="1"> Investing in Agricultural Production and Marketing Capacity in Palestine
The agricultural sector has a strategic role in achieving food security and generating employment in most developing economies, yet it remains one of the least advanced sectors in Palestine, with a continually declining productive capacity. Although the sector’s contribution to employment has remained stable to some extent, hovering around 6.7% in recent years, the value added of the agricultural sector declined by 2.3% in 2021, following an even bigger drop (by 9.1%) in the pandemic conditions of 2020. Palestinian agricultural imports ($956.3m) far exceed agricultural exports ($165.6m), leaving the sector with high exposure to trade shocks.1 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="2"> Despite sharing a similar natural environment, Palestine’s crop yield per dunum is, on average, half of that in Jordan and only 43% of that in Israel.2 While a variety of factors contribute to low productivity levels, Israeli-imposed restrictions remain the main obstacle. For example, UNCTAD estimates a 20-33% decline in agricultural productivity since Israel enforced restrictions on the importation of fertilisers under the dual-use list. Other restrictions imposed by Israel, such as those related to access to agricultural land, water resources, seedlings and livestock imports, in addition to stringent inspection processes, have also had a detrimental impact on Palestinian agriculture.3 Other impediments, such as the limited budget allocation by the Palestinian National Authority (PNA) and the lack of a dynamic vision on how to develop the sector in line with strategic food security goals, are further reasons for the shrinking of the agricultural sector. 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="3"> As a result of these obstructions, Palestine is highly dependent on food imports, with at least $4.6 billion (32.4%) of Palestinians’ annual expenditure going to imported food products. This poses a significant risk to food security, particularly in periods of rising commodity prices globally. According to the World Food Program (WFP), 31.2% of the Palestinian population is food insecure. The situation is much worse in Gaza, where 64.4% are food insecure.4
The aftermath of the global pandemic and the Russian invasion of Ukraine, with market closures and supply chain disruptions, has reaffirmed the need for major investment in this strategic sector, and its importance for self-sufficiency and economic resilience. 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="4"> The Jordanian Palestinian Agricultural Marketing Company (JPACO)
On 3 August, the Jordanian Palestinian Agricultural Marketing Company (JPACO) opened its Palestinian branch in the Jericho Agro-Industrial Park (JAIP).5 This follows the inauguration of the company’s Jordanian branch in Amman back in April of this year.6
JPACO was founded in December 2021 to boost the agriculture sectors in both countries by expanding agricultural production, improving quality and price competitiveness of products, and maximising supply to local and global markets. On 25 July 2022, JPACO had reached an agreement to export 500 tonnes of Palestinian-produced peppers worth $1 million through a number of international intermediary companies.7 This unique public-private, Jordanian- Palestinian joint venture suggests a feasible way forward to relieve some of the bottlenecks faced in marketing, while drawing on the best practices of agricultural marketing boards, which were a key to success for many developing countries. 
</paragraph>

</page>