<page>
<paragraph number="1"> Al-Rabia Feed and Grain Factory
On 29 June, Dr. Mohammed Mustafa, Chairman of the Palestine Investment Fund’s (PIF) Board of Directors, highlighted developments in launching the Al-Rabia Feed and Grain Factory in the west Hebron area and confirmed the operational plans for the year 2023.8
The construction of the $20m project started in 2020, with a planned production capacity of 40,000 tons per year in the first phase, and 80,000 tons per year in later phases. The project also includes much-needed grain silos with a storage capacity of about 20,000 tons, which was a long-standing demand of farmers and agro-business in Palestine. The project is strategically located in the Hebron governorate, which holds 38.7% and 28.1% of the West Bank cow and lamb population, respectively.9 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="2"> This project is of great significance for the agricultural sector and the Palestinian economy more generally, as it addresses an acute gap in the local production and storage of animal feed. Currently, local production of animal feed is far from meeting demand. In the West Bank alone, animal feed imports amount to around 550,000 tons annually, while local production does not exceed 250,000 tons or 31.3% of market demand. In 2019, Palestine imported $289.1m worth of animal feed, in addition to $86.1m worth of wheat, barely, maize and soybeans (main inputs used in the production of animal feed).10 Palestine also lacks adequate grain-storing capacity, as it depends on the private sector’s stockpiles and Israel’s storage facilities to meet its population’s immediate consumption needs.11 Furthermore, due to the conflict in Ukraine, the cost of animal feed, and particularly wheat bran, has risen by 60% in the West Bank, exacerbating the existing burden on Palestinian herders. 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="3"> Agricultural Census
On 16 June, the Palestinian Central Bureau of Statistics (PCBS) and the Ministry of Agriculture published the preliminary findings of the 2021 Agricultural Census, conducted every decade and providing vitally important official data for future planning and investment. The Census indicates that 18.5% of the West Bank total area and 24.6% of the Gaza total area are cultivated.
The area of agricultural land increased by 20.3% between 2010 (912 thousand dunum) and 2021 (1.1m dunum). As of 2021, 61.7% of agricultural land is planted with horticultural trees (mainly olives), followed by field crops (19.8%) and vegetables (18.5%).12 The census also shows that there were 140,500 agricultural holdings in Palestine in 2021, of which 73.4% are plant holdings, 14.2% are livestock holdings, and 12.5% are mixed holdings. The number of agricultural holdings increased by 26.3% between 2010 and 2021. Historically, the division of agricultural land due to inheritance was among the main causes for the increase in agricultural holdings.13 The average area of agricultural holdings was 8.6 dunum in 2021 compared to 10.8 dunum in 2010. 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="4"> The agricultural census also shows a larger increase in layer and broiler chickens between 2010 and 2021 (236% and 228%, respectively) compared to other types of livestock. Possible reasons include the introduction of incorporated large-scale poultry farms and the Israeli restrictions imposed on cow, sheep, and goat imports.14 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="5"> Digital-financial transformation of government services
The digitisation of governmental services could play a significant part in reinforcing trust in digital payments, as well as in public services, through increased transparency and efficiency. It can also contribute to digital financial inclusion. For this reason, the Government has been playing a leading role in policy initiatives relating to digital transformation. 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="6"> e-Payments for government services
On 28 July, PalPay, a Palestinian electronic payment company, signed an agreement with the Ministry of Social Development (MoSD) to provide its services to those served by the Ministry, including the 115,000 low-income and marginalised households that benefit from the cash transfer programme.15 This will help facilitate the distribution of financial support by MoSD and its local and international partners to the most vulnerable families and make the process easier for the beneficiaries, particularly those in areas where formal financial services are not available.
On 13 July, PalPay also signed an agreement with the Al-Bireh Municipality to make its mobile and electronic payment methods available to residents wishing to pay municipal service fees, including unbanked residents.16 Other Palestinian e-payment companies, such as Maalchat and JawwalPay, are also expanding their reach and offering new innovative services. Maalchat has previously signed similar agreements with the Municipalities of Ramallah, Al-Bireh and Nablus.17 
</paragraph>

</page>