<page>
<paragraph number="1"> My Government platform
On 14 July, the Ministry of Telecommunications and Information Technology (MTIT) announced that a ministerial committee is studying the electronic payment tender for the launch of the Unified Portal for electronic government services, otherwise known as “My Government”.18 The platform will enable citizens to enquire about and pay for government services and official documents using debit and credit cards, and via e-payment platforms.
Once operational, the portal will at first provide services to resident citizens, and later expand to include those residing abroad. In a limited first phase, the portal will offer 17 out of 1,400 services currently provided by the government, 9 of which are paid services such as renewing driving licenses, renewing health insurance, or requesting certificates (e.g. bith certificates...etc). 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="2"> Palestinian workers in Israel
On 27 July, the Palestine Economic Policy Research Institute (MAS) held a round-table to discuss one of its latest reports, entitled: “The future of Palestinian labour in the Israeli labour market in light of economic and political realities”.19 More than fifty experts and representatives from local and international institutions participated in the event. The discussion was focused on the political and economic factors behind the large increase in the number of Palestinian workers in Israel and Israeli settlements, and what it bodes for the future of the Palestinian economy. 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="3"> Rapid acceleration of work in Israel
The past decade witnessed a significant increase in the number of Palestinian workers in Israel and Israeli settlements. By Q2 2022, around 210,500 Palestinians were working in Israel and Israeli settlements compared to only 78,225 in 2010, with an accelerated increase over the past five years.20 Their contribution to employment and GNI has thus increased over the same period, from 10.5% to 14.1%, and from 7.2% to 14.9%, respectively.21 However, these figures are higher when excluding the Gaza Strip (whose workers were barred from Israel for 15 years, culminating in 2021). Around a quarter of the West Bank workforce today is dependent on jobs in Israel. 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="4"> Employment in Israel has also been a main driver of private consumption over the past two years, helping the economy recover from the COVID-19 pandemic when there were very limited growth-inducing factors. In Q1 2022, as the Palestinian economy contracted by 3.1% due to a 5% drop in investment and a 19.7% drop in government spending, private consumption contributed 7.7% to growth.22 It is worth noting that at least 23% of Palestinian private consumption expenditure is on goods imported from Israel.23 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="5"> Israeli policy
The increase in the number of Palestinian workers in Israel reflects a shift in Israeli policies, particularly after the Government of Israel (GoI) issued Government Resolution 2174 in 2016, which laid the groundwork for streamlining the permit issuance process and terms of contracting to increase the number of workers in target sectors (mainly construction, agriculture and industry).24 The GoI also later introduced quotas for new target sectors where there is a shortage of workers, such as construction, agriculture and industry. In a policy shift, these sectors lately have also included high-tech, health and tourism, and starting in 2021, Israel has allowed a limited number of workers from Gaza to enter Israel.25 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="6"> Additionally, from August 2022, starting on a trial basis, 7,000 Palestinian workers in Israel will receive their salaries through bank transfers, and permits will no longer be issued for those who receive their salaries in cash.26 Firas Milhem, Governor of the Palestinian Monetary Authority (PMA), noted that once expanded, this would help shrink the recurring problem of accumulated ILS cash notes in the Palestinian market. On an annual basis, total cash inflow amounts to around ILS 20 billion, of which ILS 12- 15 billion are transported directly by Palestinian workers in Israel. Historically, Israel has imposed ceilings on the amount of shekels that its central bank is willing to accept and exchange for hard currency (currently set by the Bank of Israel at around ILS 16 billion annually).27 Excess shekel amounts have presented a huge burden, as the Palestinian banking sector continues to incur the costs of storing, insuring, and guarding large amounts of cash in its vaults.28 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="7"> Labour market disruptions
Despite its benefit in generating much-needed income, employment in Israel has also long caused a distortion in wage levels in the Palestinian labour market. Unskilled labourers in Israel earn higher salaries there compared to skilled labourers in the local market.29 As a result, domestic productive sectors such as construction, agriculture and industry are unable to attract or retain enough employees to grow and compete, as they do not have the capacity to pay higher wages. In Q1 2022, the average daily wage for Palestinian workers in Israel and Israeli settlements was ILS 271.5, compared to ILS 118 in the West Bank and ILS 55.9 in Gaza.
Higher wages in Israel cause a shortage of labour in some local sectors, particularly those that require unskilled labour. This was confirmed by the results of interviews and focus groups carried out by MAS over the past two years, which included employers, representatives of the private sector, the Palestinian Ministry of Labor, and trade unions.30 
</paragraph>

<paragraph number="8"> July Trading
Al-Quds index closed at 634.5 points on the last day of trading in July 2022, a decrease of 4.8% from the previous month.31 During the month, a total of 15.6m shares with a total value of $34.3m were traded, marking a 51% decrease in the number and 43.2% drop in the value of traded shares compared to June 2022.
On 18 July, Safa Bank (SAFABANK) was listed on the Palestine Exchange (PEX).32 This is the third Islamic bank to be listed on PEX, and the second listing this year following the listing of ARKAAN last month. Safa Bank was established in 2016 with a total capital of $75m, and it offers a range of Islamic banking products and services.33 Currently, the bank has eight branches, nine ATMs and one services office in the West Bank.
</paragraph>

</page>